Yale Medical Library Opening and Dedication
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Yale Medical Library opening and dedication
1939-1942
Ms Coll 12
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
1
2 boxes
Correspondence, printed materials, and clippings saved by Madeline Stanton, Secretary of the Historical Library, concerning the building, opening, and formal dedication of the Yale Medical Library on June 15, 1941.
Harvey Cushing/John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Yale Medical Library
Yale Medical Library. Historical Library
Biographical / Historical
The Yale Medical Library (now the Harvey Cushing/John Hay Whitney Medical Library), an addition to the Sterling Hall of Medicine designed by Grosvenor Atterbury (Yale College 1891), began to be built in late 1939, and was dedicated in a large formal ceremony on June 15, 1941. It was designed in the shape of a Y with the Historical Library in one wing and the General Medical Library in the other. The founders of the library were three physicians, book collectors, and historians of medicine: neurosurgeon Harvey Cushing (Yale College, 1891), then Sterling Professor of Neurology; John Fulton, Sterling Professor of Physiology; and Arnold C. Klebs of Nyon, Switzerland. They had agreed to donate their rare book collections to Yale if Yale would build a place to house them. That offer coalesced with the need of the Medical School to build a larger library located on the Medical School campus for current medical books and journals. The Medical School had a small library but the main collection of medical books and journals was then housed at Sterling Memorial Library. By February 1941, the General Medical Library was open for patrons. The dedication marked the opening of the Historical wing of the Library. Cushing, who had been the main advocate for the library, knew that the Library would be built, but died in October 1939 before the construction began. The year 1941 coincided with the 50th anniversary of Cushing's Yale class of 1891, which donated funds as part of its class gift to decorate the rotunda of the library in commemoration of Cushing.
Arrangement
Organized in three series: 1. Correspondence. 2. Printed materials. 3. Clippings.
Custodial History
The correspondence and first set of pamphlets were maintained by Madeline Stanton, Secretary of the Historical Library, and held by the Historical Library since its inception. Stanton collected a variant set of pamphlets and clippings which she pasted on backing and annotated for a possible notebook or scrapbook.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, printed materials, and clippings. The correspondence by John Fulton and others includes letters on organizing the program for the dedication, hundreds of handwritten and typed RSVPs to the Dean of the School of Medicine, Francis G. Blake, accepting the invitation or declining, and letters of congratulation after the ceremony. The printed materials include pamphlets issued while the library was being constructed, the invitation to the dedication, a map of the library and the exhibits on display, the "Blessing of the Books" by the Reverend George Stewart, reprints of the speeches, and an illustrated reprint on the architecture of the library. Clippings include articles from the New York Times, the New Haven Register, other newspapers, and journals.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Medical libraries -- Connecticut; Rare books; Clippings; Correspondence; Pamphlets; Atterbury, Grosvenor, 1869-1956; Blake, Francis G. (Francis Gilman), 1887-1952; Bishop, Lottie Genevieve, 1885-; Childs, Starling Winston, 1870-1946; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939; Fulton, John F. (John Farquhar), 1899-1960; Homans, John, 1877-1954; Klebs, Arnold C. (Arnold Carl), 1870-1943; Lewis, W. S. (Wilmarth Sheldon), 1895-1979; Seymour, Charles, 1885-1963; Stanton, Madeline E. (Madeline Earle); Stewart, George; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1891; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Correspondence, 1941; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence related to the dedication of the Yale Medical Library.
  - Plans for the opening ceremony, 1941 March-1941June (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Correspondence by John Fulton, Madeline Stanton, and others, maintained by Madeline Stanton.
  - Invitation lists (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with individuals after the invitation was sent (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Acceptances of invitation 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    General
    Letters of acceptance were originally in one large folder and regrets in another large folder. They have been divided into several folders for preservation.
  - Acceptances of invitation 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Acceptances of invitation 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Acceptances of invitation 4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Acceptances of invitation 5 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Regrets 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Letters of regret by those who could not attend the dedication ceremony.
  - Regrets 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Regrets 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Regrets 4 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence after the dedication ceremony, 1941 June-1941 August (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes some letters of congratulation and plans to print the speeches in the Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine.
- Printed materials, 1941-1942; Series II
  - Invitation to the opening of the Yale Medical Library (Box 2, Folder 2)
    The formal invitation came from the President and Fellows of Yale University but responses were to be sent to the Dean of the School of Medicine. Speakers included Wilmarth S. Lewis, representing the Yale Corporation; Starling W. Childs representing Harvey Cushing's Yale Class of 1891; Charles Seymour, President of Yale University; Francis G. Blake, Dean of the School of Medicine; John Homans, a Harvard surgeon who had recently spent a year at Yale; and the Rev. George Stewart, Minister of the First Presbyterian Church, Stamford, and son-in-law of Arnold C. Klebs.
  - Yale Medical Library, "Special Collections and Exhibits Arranged for Opening Ceremonies, 15 June 1941" (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Four-page brochure showing the arrangement of the Historical Library and General Medical Library.
  - George Stewart, The Blessing of the Books; Scripture and Prayer Read at the Dedication of the Yale Medical Library on Sunday XV June MDCCCCXLI (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Four-page brochure.
  - Yale University News Bureau, Press releases of speeches (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Mimeographed press releases "not to be used before 5 p.m., June 15," of the remarks at the dedication by Charles Seymour and Francis G. Blake.
  - "Dedication Ceremony of the Yale Medical Library, June 15, 1941," reprint from Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Brochure, 28 pages, reprinted from Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine 13 (1941): 863-889. It contains all the speeches from the dedication and a frontispiece consisting of a photograph of the Historical Library and a transcription of George Stewart's engraved words over the fireplace.
  - "The Yale Medical Library, Dedicated June 15, 1941," reprinted from Pencil Points, 1942 January (Box 2, Folder 7)
    This ten-page brochure reprinted from Pencil Points focuses on the architecture of the Yale Medical Library, designed by Grosvenor Atterbury, and contains photographs and diagrams.
  - Memorabilia collected by Madeline Stanton on the Yale Medical Library, 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    These materials were pasted on backing and annotated by Madeline Stanton. In addition to pamphlets already mentioned, the folder contains a note by Wilmarth Lewis stating that the decisive date for the building of the library was September 22, 1939; two pamphlets dated May 24, 1940 and April 1941 on the progress of construction and asking "Patrons of the Yale Medical Library" for funds; an undated list of exhibits and note about a reception for the Connecticut Clinical Congress; a formal pledge of the Collection of Arnold C. Klebs dated June 16, 1941; and Report of the Historical Library for 1940-1941.
  - "Documents printed in connection with the opening ceremonies", 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    In addition to previous materials on the dedication, there is a variant program with the notice of serving tea in the Beaumont Room; a variant printing of "The Blessing of the Books"; and a page on an exhibit of selected Yale University Press books at Sterling Memorial Library presented by the Class of 1891 in memory of Harvey Cushing.
- Clippings, 1939-1941; Series III
  - Newspaper clippings on the Yale Medical Library, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Clippings from the New Haven Register, the New York Times, and other papers on the building of the Yale Medical Library and on Cushing's donation of his collection.
  - Newspaper clippings on the Yale Medical Library, 1941 January-May (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper clippings on the Yale Medical Library, 1941 June-October (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Journal clippings on the Yale Medical Library, 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 13)